Two years ago here at TED
منذ عامين هنا في تيد
I reported that we had discovered
أعلنت أننا قد اكتشفنا
at Saturn, with the Cassini Spacecraft,
في زحل، بمركبة الفضاء كاسيني
an anomalously warm and geologically active region
منطقة شاذة حراريا ونشطة جيولوجيا
at the southern tip of the small Saturnine moon
في الطرف الجنوبي من أصغر قمر لزحل
Enceladus, seen here.
أنسيلادوس، كما يبدو هنا
This region seen here for the first time
هذه المنطقة التي رأيتموها هنا للمرة الأولى
in the Cassini image taken in 2005. This is the south polar region,
في صورة كاسيني المأخوذة عام 2005. هذه هي منطقة القطب الجنوبي
with the famous tiger-stripe fractures crossing the south pole.
بتشققات النمر الشهيرة التي تعبر القطب الجنوبي
And seen just recently in late 2008,
ورأينها مؤخرا في أواخر 2008
here is that region again,
ها هي تلك المنطقة
now half in darkness because the southern hemisphere
نصفها في الظلام لأن النصف الجنوبي
is experiencing the onset of August
يشهد بداية شهر أغسطس
and eventually winter.
وتدريجيا الشتاء
And I also reported that we'd made this mind-blowing discovery --
كما أعلنت أننا اكتشفنا هذا الأمرالمذهل
this once-in-a-lifetime discovery
هذا الاكتشاف النادر
of towering jets
لأعمدة متدفقة
erupting from those fractures at the south pole,
تتفجر من تلك التشققات في القطب الجنوبي
consisting of tiny water ice crystals
تتكون من بلورات ثلجية صغيرة
accompanied by water vapor
يرافقها بخار ماء
and simple organic compounds like carbon dioxide and methane.
ومركبات عضوية بسيطة مثل ثاني أكسيد الكربون والميثان
And at that time two years ago
وفي ذلك الوقت منذ عامين
I mentioned that we were speculating
ذكرت أننا نتوقع
that these jets might in fact be geysers,
أن تلك النافثات قد تكون في الواقع ينابيع ساخنة
and erupting from pockets
تتفجر من فجوات
or chambers of liquid water underneath the surface,
أو حجرات من الماء السائل تحت السطح
but we weren't really sure.
ولكننا لم نكن متأكدين
However, the implications of those results --
ومع ذلك، فإن آثار تلك النتائج
of a possible environment within this moon
لمناخ محتمل على هذا القمر
that could support prebiotic chemistry,
يستطيع دعم كيمياء قبل الحيوية
and perhaps life itself --
وربما الحياة
were so exciting that, in the intervening two years,
كانت مثيرة جدا لدرجة أننا في العامين التاليين
we have focused more on Enceladus.
قد ركزنا أكثر على أنسيلادوس
We've flown the Cassini Spacecraft
لقد طرنا بمركبة كاسيني
by this moon now several times,
قرب هذا القمر الآن عدة مرات
flying closer and deeper into these jets,
نطير أقرب وأعمق داخل هذه النافثات
into the denser regions of these jets,
إلى المناطق الأكثف من تلك النافثات
so that now we have come away with some
ما مكنا الآن من الخروج ببعض
very precise compositional measurements.
بقراءات دقيقة للمكونات
And we have found
ووجدنا
that the organic compounds coming from this moon
أن المكونات العضوية الصادرة عن هذا القمر
are in fact more complex than we previously reported.
هي في الواقع أكثر تعقيدا مما أعلنا سابقا
While they're not amino acids,
مع أنها ليست أحماضا أمينية
we're now finding things like
فنحن نجد أمورا مثل
propane and benzene,
البروبين والبنزين
hydrogen cyanide, and formaldehyde.
سيانيد الهيدروجين، والفورمالديهايد
And the tiny water crystals here
وبلورات الماء الصغيرة هنا
now look for all the world
الآن تبدو للعالم أجمع
like they are frozen droplets of salty water,
كأنها قطرات مجمدة من ماء مالح
which is a discovery that suggests
وهو اكتشاف يوحي
that not only do the jets come from
أن النافثات لا تأتي فحسب من
pockets of liquid water,
فجوات من الماء السائل
but that that liquid water is in contact with rock.
ولكن أن هذا الماء السائل يلامس أحجارا
And that is a circumstance
وهذا ظرف
that could supply the chemical energy
يمكن أن يوفر الطاقة الكيميائية
and the chemical compounds needed to sustain life.
والمكونات الكيميائية المطلوبة للمحافظة على الحياة
So we are very encouraged by these results.
لذا فهذه النتائج مشجعة جدا
And we are much more confident now than we were two years ago
ونحن أكثر ثقة الآن مما كنا عليه قبل عامين
that we might indeed
أننا فعلا قد
have on this moon, under the south pole,
نجد على هذا القمر، تحت القطب الجنوبي
an environment or a zone that is hospitable to living organisms.
مناخا أو منطقة ملائمة للكائنات الحية
Whether or not there are living organisms there, of course,
ما إذا كانت هناك كائنات حية هناك، بطبيعة الحال
is an entirely different matter.
هي مسألة مختلفة تماما
And that will have to await the arrival,
وسيتعين أن ننتظر وصول
back at Enceladus,
عودة إلى إينسيلادوس
of the spacecrafts, hopefully some time in the near future,
السفينة الفضائية، في المستقبل القريب
specifically equipped to address that particular question.
ومجهزة تحديدا للإجابة عن ذلك السؤال تحديدا
But in the meantime I invite you to imagine the day
ولكن في الوقت الراهن أدعوكم جميعا لتخيل اليوم
when we might journey to the Saturnine system,
الذي نسافر فيه إلى مجموعة زحل
and visit the Enceladus interplanetary geyser park,
ونزور فيه حديقة إينسيلادوس للينابيع الساخنة
just because we can.
فقط لأننا نستطيع ذلك
Thank you.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)